Hi, everyone! In this issue, we'll have a look at Git date formats.
I've mentioned it in "log" and "reflog" video and in some other ones
I've mentioned them in screencast edition about 'log' and 'reflog' commands, so as in other moments
where I had to pass a date to Git, or specify a date output format.
where I had to pass date to Git, or ask Git to output it in predefined format.
First of all, lets have a look how one can set a date format.
Fristly, let's find out how to pass date to Git.
Heres a list of examples:
As you might have noticed, Git can accept almost any format.
As you may see Git almost accept any format.
Dates precision is seconds.
Dates are accurate at second.
If dates time zone is not set local time is used by default.
If dates haven't time zone. The local time zone is presumed.
One can also set the date without setting the time. Like here.
You may also set the date without time. As here
If you use the slash sign "/" month will go first.
If you use slash sign '/ ',
month goes first
I mean "month/day/year".
I mean 'month/day/year'.
Last row dates are in Unix timestamp format.
Last row contains dates in Unix timestamp
Thats number of seconds that have elapsed since January 1, 1970 00:00 UTC
means, number of seconds that passed from 1st January, 1970
It's a widely used format to represent a date as unique number.
It's very used format for date representation as unique number.
Its used in software development and git understands it too.
Generally it is used in development. Git use it also.
As for now everything looks pretty simple, isnt't it?
For the moment everything is pretty simple. Isn't it?!
It gets fun when the date is set partly.
Actually the fun begins when you set the date partially
I've created a test repository for demonstrational purposes
I'll show you in a moment, within the repo I created before
in which commits were pushed every 3 hours.
in which commits are pushed every 3 hours
I'll print them in a short format. So that unnecessary data is not shown.
I'll print out them in short format. So that nothing unnecessary will be in.
And we'll get into it at once.
Also let's review
If I ask Git for commits till the 2nd of January
If I ask Git for commit until 2nd January
What do you think this command will result in?
What will print out suchlike command?
Maybe
It should print everything up to the 2nd of January inclusively?
Is it going to output everything from 2nd January and earlier, inclusive?
I mean these commits.
I mean, are they those commits?
Or, maybe it should print all commits till the 2nd January midnight?
Or, maybe, is it going to output commits until 0 hours 0 minutes of the 2nd January?
I mean those that were before this date, these ones.
those commits which are until set date
these one!
Actually, none of the above.
The answer is none of them.
Let's run it.
I'll run them
As you can see we have commits done on the 2nd of January.
As you may see the output last with some commits from 2nd January,
but not all of them. What happened?
but not all of them
What happened? Easy
If time is not set, current time is used.
If we hadn't set the time, it goes with current time.
I have about 4PM now so Git used it to get this date.
My time is 4 PM, so Git catch the date in that format
Lets have a look at some more examples to get a better understanding of these subtle moments.
For better understanding let's review some more examples
Imagine its 30th of January, 2018
Imagine that today is 30 January, 1918
12:30 AM
I will show the actual dates on the left and the way git perceives them on the right.
On the left side I will show you dates, and on the right side - how Git actually understands them
We've seen some of these before, namely if we set the date only,
Some of these we've seen before. Exactly, if we pass the date only
current time will be used.
it will take the current time.
Let's move on.
Let's move on
If you set the time only
You can set time only
then the output will use the current date.
then it will output only the current date
In this case 3:30 PM means 3:30 PM, today.
In this case 3:30 PM, means 3:30 PM of the current date
Time format can be like this.
The date format also can look like this.
I didnt set the timezone here.
i didn't pass the timezone anywhere.
Its quite straightforward here.
Here is pretty simple.
If no timezone was specified it will use the current one.
If you didn't pass the timezone it will assign the current one
Lets move on.
Let's go further
Git, together with various manuals often use the following format:
In Git as in any other documentation mostly it's used that format
So instead of pointing out a specific date and time we use an interval
so we didn't pass certain date and time but only the lapse
It's 3 weeks here. But it could be hours, days, months and so on...
Here it is 3 weeks. But also could be hours, days, months, and so on...
Git interprets this as a relative date
Git interpret it like a relative date
In this particular case 3 weeks ago to the current moment.
it means 3 weeks ago from this moment
You have to realize
that all these notes are identical.
that all those notes are identical
For example, I can set 3 days
can, do without "s", actually
also without 's'
meaning singular
meaning singular. And this will also work as Git doesnt care about it too much.
And this also will work, because Git doesn't care much about it
I can even write "3."
I can even write 3. dot.
days.
Like that. All the same.
Like that. Pretty the same
The "." is often used for convenience
The dot is used for convenience
because you dont need to wrap the date with quotes if dot is used.
setting it around date let you skip quotes
Word "ago"
Word 'ago'
which is often used as well
which is often used usually
is a pure decoration.
it's only for beautifier purpose
One can type something like "bla-bla-bla" instead
you can enter anything you want. For example, 'blah-blah-blah'
and it will do the same.
same thing
Git ignores it.
Git just ignores it
One more example
Git allows you to specify a more complex interval.
Git also allows you to set more complex interval
In this case it's 1 year and 2 months and a little
In this case it is a year and 2 months and some stuff
from this moment.
from this moment
I can use digits names, instead of digits themselves
I can pass their names instead of digits
0 - "zeor", "one, two, three" and so on, till 10.
0 - 'zero', 'one, two, three'... and so on, until 10
It can only count to 10.
10 actually is the limit number
Some more of this kind of tricks:
One more trick
For example, "yesterday" means yesterday,
'yesterday'
doesn't mean yesterday evening
doesn't mean yesterday morning, but yesterday at the same time of the day
doesn't event mean yesterday morning, but yesterday at the same time
exactly 24 hours ago.
However, if we need yesterday morning
However, If we need yesterday morning date and time
it's easy to make
It is easy to get it
Let's make it yesterday at 3 AM.
Let's set not only yesterday, but for example, yesterday 3 AM.
And here we go. The commits till 3 AM.
See. This is the commit from 3 AM.
There are other reserved words that you can use:
There are also other defined specific words
"midnight"
'midnight'
"noon"
'noon'
and "tea" - 5 o'clock, tea time.
and 'tea' - 5 o'clock, tea time
The difference between these words
The difference between defining words in format
and setting the exact time,
and setting straightforward the actual time is this
like 5 PM,
For example, 5 PM
is that if we are behind the forementioned time
What If that time didn't come yet
then it will take 5 PM yesterday.
then it will take yesterday 5 PM data
In other words in our case
Other speaking, in our example
We are having 12:30, right?
We consider that our time is 12:30 AM.
Less than 5 PM
Less then 5 PM
Therefore "tea" will use 5 PM yesterday
so 'tea' will pull yesterday date
as it's written here
as it's written there
This special names
This specific designation
are making sure that the date will not refer to future.
prove that date won't be outputed in future
In practice they are barely used at all.
In practice they are barely in use
Another pecularity
More exotic
is that one can use "last" word
you can set keyword 'last'
followed by the day of the week.
after which goes day of the week
For example: last friday.
For example, last Friday
Sometimes it can be useful.
Sometimes you get used to it
Finally, 2 more examples
Lastly, 2 more examples
"never"
'never'
and "now".
'now'
These are the ones that are used most often
Those labels are mostly used
when we need to set an expiration date for anything.
when we set expirate date for anything we want
For example, lets recall that
Again, I'll remind you that
time to store a record for the "reflog"
storage record for 'reflog' time
is sroted in the "gc.refLogExpire"
is stored in variable
variable
'gc.refLogExpire'
Its set in the relative format by default
By default it's set in relative format
and is equal to 90 days
so when cleaning the garbage
so as at garbage cleaning
it subtracts 90 days from the current moment.
it will subtract 90 days from current moment
Any records older than that are to be deleted
Any old records are going to be deleted
and those newer - remain.
and those fresh - stay
Let's change it to "never".
Let's change it on 'never'
Technically "never" means zero timestamp.
Technically 'never' originates zero timestamp
In other words
in other words
1st of Janyart, 1970.
1st January, 1970
So, again, technically
so, again, that's technically
by setting "never"
Setting 'never'
we ask Git to delete all the records
We tell Git that we have to delete records
till 1970.
until 1970 year
But we dont have such an old ones
but we didn't have such old records
therefore nothing was deleted.
is why nothing is erased
For that we set "never".
For this we set 'never'
never's opposite value
'never's opposite notion
is "now"
is 'now'
which is used in a little bit different way.
which is used as different type.
For example
I want to delete all the records from "reflog"
I want to delete all records from 'reflog'
I run "git reflow expire"
I run 'git reflog expire'
command to delete
command 'expire' to delete
add an expire parameter to it
attach a parameter
date till which I want it to be deleted
in form of a date that I have to delete
in our case its "now"
In our case, I set period until 'now'
And "all" means that it has to go through all the links.
And 'all' mean that it has to go though all links provided
and perform this operation for all of them
and do same task over each of them
Usually
"now" means "at the current moment"
'now' means current state
but when it's used for the expiration date
but when it's set as an expiration date
theres a little hack for that in Git
it is the Git's little hack
"now" means a far future date,
because 'now' starts to mean a far date from the future
in this case
we want to delete all the records
we want to delete all records
till some date in the future
until some future date
that means everything.
for this case it's everything.
Or we can use "all" instead of "now"
You may set instead 'now', 'all' parameter
as its a historical pseudoname for "now"
it is the historical pseudoname for 'now'
which is only working for the expiration dates.
which works only for expirate dates
So if I run this now
So, I'll run this now
then all "reflogs" are going to be deleted.
then everything from 'reflog' will be cleaned out
These are all the examples so far.
Those were some practical examples
How to set the date in Git.
to set date in Git.
As you see there are some subtleties
but once you grasp it you can use them quite comfortable.
but as you get acquainted with them, you can use date formats pretty easily
We'll talk about the output formats further.
Next we'll talk about output formats